Eliakim Littell Correspondence
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Eliakim Littell Correspondence 1819-1869 (bulk 1825-1852)
MSS85318
Littell, Eliakim, 1797-1870
65 items
1 container
.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Editor and publisher. Correspondence largely devoted to Littell's work as publisher of Museum of Foreign Literature and Science and Littell's Living Age. Notable correspondents include James Buchanan, John C. Calhoun, DeWitt Clinton, Andrew Jackson, William Hickling Prescott, and Thomas Jefferson.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Buchanan, James, 1791-1868--Correspondence.; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850--Correspondence.; Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828--Correspondence.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Littell, Eliakim, 1797-1870.; Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859--Correspondence.
Subjects
American periodicals.; Education, Higher.; Literature--Periodicals.; Public universities and colleges.
Titles
Eliakim Littell papers; Littell's living age.; Museum of foreign literature and science.
Occupations
Editors.; Publishers.
Provenance
The correspondence of Eliakim Littell, editor and publisher, was given to the Library of Congress by Charles A. Platt in 2006.
Access and Restrictions
The correspondence of Eliakim Littell is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1797, Jan. 2 Born, Burlington, N.J.
1819 1821 Published the National Recorder, a weekly literary paper, Philadelphia, Pa.
1822 1844 Published the Museum of Foreign Literature and Science, a monthly magazine, Philadelphia, Pa.
1844 Began publishing the Littell's Living Age, a weekly literary periodical, Boston, Mass.
1855 Began publishing the Panorama of Life and Literature, a monthly magazine, Boston, Mass.
1833 Drafted the Compromise Tariff of 1833, carried through Congress by Henry Clay
1870, May 17 Died, Brookline, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondence of Eliakim Littell (1797-1870) spans the years 1819-1869, with the bulk of the material dating from 1825 to 1852. The collection details Littell's work as publisher of Museum of Foreign Literature and Science and Littell's Living Age, Littell's interest in establishing public institutions for higher learning, as well as invitations, thank-you notes, and recommendations. Notable correspondents include James Buchanan, John C. Calhoun, DeWitt Clinton, Andrew Jackson, William Hickling Prescott, and Thomas Jefferson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
Container List
- Breckinridge, [R. J.], 1861 (Box 1)
- Bryant, William Cullen, 1851, 1860 (Box 1)
- Buchanan, James, 1851 (Box 1)
- Bury, Charlotte Campbell, Lady, 1834 (Box 1)
- Calhoun, John C., 1819, 1825, 1833-1834 (Box 1)
- Chase, Philander, undated (Box 1)
- Edgeworth, Maria, 1826 (Box 1)
- Clinton, DeWitt, 1825-1827 (Box 1)
- Everett, Edward 1825, 1849 (Box 1)
- Hall, S. C. (Samuel Carter), 1869 (Box 1)
- Holmes, Oliver Wendell, undated (Box 1)
- Horne, Thomas Hartell, 1851 (Box 1)
- Irving, Washington, 1838 (Box 1)
- Jackson, Andrew, 1825-1826 (Box 1)
- Jefferson, Thomas, 1825 (Box 1)
- Kent, James, 1829 (Box 1)
- King, Preston 1861 (Box 1)
- Mann, Horace, 1844 (Box 1)
- Miller, Sylvanus, 1825-1826 (Box 1)
- Peale, Rembrandt, 1831 (Box 1)
- Prescott, William Hickling, 1854-1857 (Box 1)
- Quincy, Josiah, 1859 (Box 1)
- Seward, William Henry, 1840, 1852 (Box 1)
- Sumner, Charles, 1851, 1862 (Box 1)
- Silliman, [B.], 1831 (Box 1)
- Story, Joseph, 1825 (Box 1)
- Taylor, Zachary, 1848-1849 (Box 1)
- Ticknor, George, Undated (Box 1)
- White, William, 1835 (Box 1)
- Whittier, [J.], 1858 (Box 1)
- Whittier, [P.], 1858 (Box 1)